Guide to the Centennial Oral History Project Oral Histories 1982-1988
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
- Series 1: One-on-one Interviews
  - Stone, Linda S. Anthropology - Alumni. Professor, February 7, 1986; Dahl, Kathleen A.; 1 tapes (Box 17)
    Personal background. WSU career, 1981-present. Undergraduate years at WSU in the 1960s. Women in anthropology. Changes in student attitudes. The Anthropology department's attitude. Colleagues. Anthropology's relationship with Administration. International Development Program. Relationship with students. Faculty salaries and morale. Reputation of WSU's Anthropology department. Changes (and lack of) in Pullman. Stone's goals for the Department.
  - Strait, Leland C. Agriculture, January 15, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 17)
    Personal biography. Work on Indian reservations. Professional career at WSU, 1956-76 as County Extension Agent in Indian Affairs under WSC; conference and short courses coordinator for College of Agriculture; and Assistant Director of Resident Instruction for College of Agriculture. Evaluation of short courses. Advising students. The future of the College of Agriculture. Retirement activities.
    Photograph of Leland and Freda Strait, June, 1979.
  - Stratton, David H. History - Chair, November 12, 1986; Hall, David; 2 tapes (Box 18)
    FIRST MINUTES OF TAPE INAUDIBLE - STATIC. WSU career, 1962-present. Courses taught. Personal research. Publications. Professional activities. American Studies Program. Chairmanship and goals. History department - declining enrollment, early impressions, faculty, financial crisis, and undergraduate, graduate, and foreign students. Teaching versus research dilemma.
  - Sunnell, Agnes Home Economics - Extension, December 6, 1986; Hard, Margaret; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Academic and professional career at WSU, 1942-58. Research and extension work in Tacoma, King County, and Yakima. Extensive discussion on work and life in West Pakistan, 1954-56 (a WSU international development program). Colleagues at WSU. Comments on WSU's support and enthusiasm shown towards her work.
  - Thompson, Albert Foreign Languages and Division of Humanities - Dean, May 2, 1985; Elder, James; 2 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Professional career at WSU, 1930-1964. Reasons for coming to WSC. Administrative policies of four WSU Presidents. Post-WWII development - enrollment and physical expansion of the campus. Experiences as chairman of Humanities and Dean of College of Arts and Sciences. Retirement. Buildings on WSU campus.
    Report entitled "The Checkered Career of the Department of Foreign Languages and Literatures," by A. Thompson
  - Thonney, Larry Pullman business - Photography and Dairy Farming, June 17, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Impressions of WSU. Experiences at WSU - selling milk to dairy on campus, social life - 1945-1948, students, private dairy in Troy Hall, photographic work on campus, dances, student attitudes, 4-H, and FFA. Effects of WWII on campus and farm life. Relationship and affect of WSU on local business. Attitude toward education. Religious activities of late 1940s. Family members who are WSU graduates. Impressions of WSU's future.
  - Thonney, Phyllis Alumni - General Studies, 1988 (Began 1946, returned 1985), July 28, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Family members who are WSU graduates. Impressions of WSU. Impact of VWVII veterans on WSU campus. Student experiences at WSU - classes, living conditions, social activities, student/teacher relationships, rules, work, and volunteer work. Married couples and student housing.Campus health care, 1946-1948. Building changes at WSU. Returning as a student in 1985. Differences between student community and Pullman community.
  - Thoney, Steven Alumni - Agricultural Education, 1975. MA, Animal Science,1978, October 4, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Family members who are WSU graduates. Reasons for choosing WSU. Requirements for agriculture. Attitude toward WSU. Reasons for choosing major. Student experiences at WSU - classes, a typical day, wife, grades, fraternities, professors, and social and religious activities. Thoughts on studying and impact of courses on career. Drug use on campus. Professional career as orchardist in Prosser. Support of Greek system. Cougar athletics. Current contact with WSU. Political support for WSU. Needs of the state. National issues during the 1970s.
  - Thonney, Walter Pullman business - farming, July 27, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Grade school and high school experiences in Pullman. Experiences as an Army nurse on WSU campus during the Flu Epidemic of 1918. Army service.
  - Tjomsland, Arnold C. Education, May 27, 1982; Grunewald, Marjorie; 2 tapes (Box 18)
    Biography of Tjomsland. Work with State Office of Public Instruction, 1950-1960. Capital Outlay Program for Washington. Design and construction of schools in the state. Professional career at WSU, 1960-1979. Department of Education. Retirement and work outside of the United States. Outstanding issues in education today.
  - Urdal, Lloyd Education - Chair, February 9, 1984; Grunewald, Marjorie; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background and education. WSU career, 1955-83. First chair of Education department, 1964. Education program - heavy loads, chair duties, growth, transition to department, growth of specialty areas, and minority programs. Current problems in education and adult education. Pluses and minuses of chairmanship. Planning and building of Cleveland Hall and the Education Library. Faculty cooperation and social activities. Retirement.
  - Vatnsdal, Mildred Mathematics Alumni, 1924. Instructor. Faculty Wife - J.R. Vatnsdal, Mathematics, June 3, 1986; DeTemple, Duane; 1 tapes (Box 18)
    Personal background. Student days at WSC - athletics, buildings/facilities, professors, majors, and sororities.Professional career as high school teacher and coach. Personal background on Vatnsdal's husband, J. Russell Vatnsdal, a professor of Mathematics at WSU. Mildred Vatnsdal's professional career at WSU, 1930-1932. Mathematics department - teaching loads, chairmen, association with the College of Engineering. Taught Air Corps students during WWII. Establishment of retirement program at WSU.
  - Vogel, Orville A. Agronomy and Soils, USDA, March 28, 1984; Rasmussen, Lowell; 3 tapes (Box 19)
    Wheat variety and disease research. WSU career, 1931-76. Cooperation with WSU. Team research. Cooperation and support from farmers and wheat organizations. Technology improvements for wheat research. Federal and state colleagues. Problems with the program. Importance of WSU's contributions to the region, and importance of endowments to WSU. The Vogel Fund for the support of research and graduate students. Western Wheat Quality Laboratory.
  - Waterman, Albert D. Education, June 23, 1982; Grunewald, Marjorie; 1 tapes (Box 19)
    Personal background. Career at WSU, 1952-77. Early days at WSU and colleagues. Work with professional organizations. Problems and projects dealt with - selection of superintendents, school projections (Kellogg Project in the Columbia Basin), and school district policies. Changes in school administration. Education curriculum at WSU. Discussion of Comparative Education Society tour of Eastern-bloc countries. Department's outreach to public schools. Current and future issues in education. Education department fishing trips.
    Vita (missing page 1).
  - Webster, Dorothy Alumni - Mathematics & Education, 1927, August 18, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 19)
    Personal background. Family members who have graduated from WSU. Student days at WSC - finances, dining hall rules, athletics, social life, buildings, fashions, dormitory living, and classes.
  - Webster, Emma Lou Alumni - Home Economics, 1930, August 18, 1986; Thonney, Phyllis; 1 tapes (Box 19)
    Personal background. Family members who are WSU graduates. Student days at WSU - classes, job, dormitory living, graduation, finances, equipment, typical day, dining hall, and athletics.
  - Weller, Harry Architecture, May 31, 1983; Lilles, Linda; 8 tapes (Box 19)
    Personal biography. Student days at WSC, 1919-23. Professional career at WSC and WSU, 1928-66. Discussion of the Architecture department, including curriculum, faculty, enrollment, architectural engineering degree, and the split between the University Architect's Office and the Department of Architectural Engineering in 1946. Also, design, construction, location, and use of various buildings on campus. Work with architects, 1923-28. The Great Depression and WWII years at WSC. Weller's teaching style. Professional organizations. Issues in architecture today. Retirement activities. Mission of a land-grant university.
    Several newspaper articles, photocopies of WSU buildings and architectural drawings, and Weller family history. Also, M.A.S.C. container list for Harry Charles Weller collection.
  - Wells, Donald A. #1 Philosophy - Chair, July 25, 1985; Elder, James H.; 1 tapes (Box 20)
    Personal background. Professional WSU career, 1948-1969. Establishment of the Philosophy department and its expansion. McCarthyism in the Pacific Northwest. Events leading up to President Wilson Compton's resignation. Change in election of department chairs. Composition of the Philosophy department. Reaction to Wells' opposition to the Vietnam War. Teaching at the University of Illinois, Chicago Circle. Account of Wilson Compton's aquisition of Priest Lake property, known as Beaver Creek Camp Association.
  - Wells, Donald A. #2 Philosophy - Chair, August 19, 1987; Brown, Barbara; 1 tapes (Box 20)
    Philosophy department - faculty, facilities, graduate program, and chairmanship. McCarthyism and WSU. Development of the Philosophy department during the 1950s.
  - Wysong, Mary History - Administrative Assistant, November 7, 1986; Hall, David; 1 tapes (Box 20)
    Professional career at WSU beginning in 1942, then intermittently. Then, returned in 1970 as secretary to the History department. Retired in 1988. Impressions of the History department. Other History department secretaries. Graduate students. Faculty. Personal background. Chairmen.
  - Yothers, Robert A. Alumni - Political Science, 1930s, December 11, 1986; Stimson, William; 2 tapes (Box 20)
    Extensive discussion on Student Strike of 1936 and Yothers' role in it as chairman.
  - Young, Leonard W. Agriculture - Experiment Stations, April 22, 1985; Bertramson, B. Rodney; 2 tapes (Box 20)
    Personal background. Professional career and duties, 1936-67. Recollections of early WSU campus. Administrative processes, 1930s and 1940s. Young's publication, "75th Anniversary of Washington Agricultural Experiment Stations History." Dean Edward Johnson's administration. President Compton's ideas. President Holland's administration. Student Strike of 1936. Johnson Hall. World War II years. Columbia Basin development. Colleagues. Unity of the various agricultural units. Experiment stations.
    Two photos of Young and Bertramson.
- Series 2: Golden Grad Interviews
  - Keith P. Jones, William A. and Edith Steward Hooper, Guy P. Miller, May 31, 1984; Anne Freeman (Box 21-22)
  - E. L. Steinke, Gustav and Jessica C. Bliesner, Virginia Harger, Elizabeth B. Hartup, May 31, 1984; Marjorie Grunewald (Box 21-22)
  - Shirley Greening Morgan, Roy T. Olson, Paul F. Schedler, Wilma Ingle Hill, May 31, 1984; Anne Freeman (Box 21-22)
  - Theodore S. Borg, Tobey Leonard Henrichsen, Catherine Diener Simpson, May 31, 1984; Richard Hamm (Box 21-22)
  - Irwin A. Davis, Lindsay Kinney, John E. Fowler, Fritz Vawter, May 31, 1984; Richard Hamm (Box 21-22)
  - Wilbur D. Simons, Zylda Elliot, Evelyn K. Hickman, Robert Emerson, Claude Irwin, May 31, 1984; Andy Tidrick (Box 21-22)
  - Jervis D. Swannack, Edward M. Gaines, Robert G. Evans, May 31, 1984; Andy Tidrick (Box 21-22)
  - Kenyon T. Bement, H. DeWayne Kreager, John W. Kelly, Loran P. Richey, May 31, 1984; David L. Hood (Box 21-22)
  - Dorothy Lois Smith-Kenney, Carville E. and Dorothy H. Sparks, May 31, 1984; Margery Sharkey (Box 21-22)
  - Bernadine Du Bois, Cliff M. Irvin, Ruth Klumb, Donald W. Stevenson, Helen A. Minkler, May 31, 1984; Margery Sharkey (Box 21-22)
  - Mary Ena Hall Link, M. C. "Mel" Hougan, William H. Munson, Marie Trupp Krieger, May 31, 1984; David L. Hood (Box 21-22)
  - Bernice Snyder, Erva S. Mosher, Oswald Gates, May 31, 1984; Marjorie Grunewald (Box 21-22)
  - Walter P. and Enis Wallace, May 8, 1985; Lisa M. Donaldson (Box 21-22)
  - Lester and Clair Winter, May 10, 1985; Lisa Donaldson (Box 21-22)
  - Elinore Crowley Coogan, May 10, 1985; William E. Brandt (Box 21-22)
  - Donald E. Coogan and Wendell H. Clark, May 10, 1985; David Seamans (Box 21-22)
  - L. Gordon (father) and Larry G. Soderholm, May 10, 1985; B. Rodney Bertramson (Box 21-22)
  - Harvey H. Olsen, April 28, 1986; B. Rodney Bertramson (Box 21-22)
  - John B. Kinney and Richard O. Moss, May 8, 1986; David Seamans (Box 21-22)
  - Mary "Peg" Hoenack, Dorothy Flynn, Ella A. Frantsen, May 8, l986; William E. Brandt (Box 21-22)
  - Rolf B. Jorgensen, May 8, 1986; Grant A. Harris (Box 21-22)
  - Lawrence Giles, May 8, 1986; Marjorie Grunewald (Box 21-22)
  - Harry E. Goldsworthy, May 8,1986; Terrence G. Popravak, Jr. (Box 21-22)
  - Harold and Evelyn Miller, May 9, 1986; B. Rodney Bertramson (Box 21-22)
  - Kay Bell and Garry M. Cameron, May 7, 1987; Rod Commons (Box 21-22)
  - Roundtable: History of WSU Physics Program. Professors Band, Barker, Butler, Riggins, 1970 (Box 21-22)
- Series 3: Paperwork
  - Paperwork relating to interviews., 3 (Box 22)